Guide to the Ipas Records, 1965-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Executive and Management Files, 1965-2006, (7 boxes)
  - Contraceptive timeline 2000, K. Rogo objectives 2000, Internal newsletter 2000, Staff meeting 2000, Bylaws 2000, China white paper 2000, L. Maguire correspondence 2000, President's message to Board 00, Objectives 2000, One pager on Ipas work 2000, Legislation 2000, Matrix guidelines 00, Speech to LAC region 2000, Key initiatives 2000-2001, Euro-donors 2000-2001, Staff 2000-2001, Results framework 2000-2001, Support staff task force 2000-2002, HR 2000-2003, World Health Organization meeting 2000, Eurodonors 2001, Senior staff 2001, Franchise information 2001, Planning and evaluation 2001, Interviewing 2001, Cluster meetings 2001-2002, Internal procedures 2001-2002, R and E 2001-2002, Staff bios 2001-2002, L. Maguire correspondence 2001, Global Health Council 2001, Gag Rule 2001, September 11 2001, L. Maguire correspondence 2002, Adolescents 2002, Dakar PAC 2002, Paris trip 2002, 63iii 2002, Guyana 2002, Gag Rule 2002, Internal reports 2002, Personnel policy 2002, Priorities 2002, Structure 2002, ET retreats 2002-2003, ET meetings 2002-2004, Asia 2003, Henry David party 2003, Comms Advisory Group 2003, Board 2003, Development 03, HIV working group 2003, Talks 2004 (Box 93)
  - Ipas Clinic Loan application 75; org chart 87, instrument distribution 88-90, MVA marketing 89/90; UNICEF/UNIPAC ltrs 89-95; MVA project guidelines 90, infection prevention 92; Swedish SIDA 92-95; USAID 93-95; CAs mtg 94; PrepCom 93 & 94; ICPD 94; 4th World Conference on Women 95; Sally Shelton 95; approaches to training late 90s; Defining Reach 96; Snr staff retreat 96; safe abortion presentation 96; new issues 98; Khama Rogo 98; Strategic Planning Notebook 98; budgeting 99; matrix org structure 99-00; staff diversity 99-02; internal newsletters 00-01; results 05; Ipas history recap and timelines 01; planning 01; publications guide 02; Executive Team 02; internal survey 02; org charts 02-04; country team leader report 03; internal newsletters 03; strategic planning and budget cuts 03; "Rosa" Nicaragua 03; program review & budget issues 04; media 04-06, strategic plan 07-11; fundraising notebook 06; President's Messages to the Board of Directors 75-06 (Box 113)
- Asia Programs, 1985-2006, (9 boxes)
  Ipas began its work in Asia in 1985 in Turkey with the supply of MVA instruments to the Ministry of Health, followed by trainings of medical providers to expand and improve menstrual regulations services. Shortly thereafter, Ipas supplied instruments and developed interventions to improve infection prevention in the Bangladesh menstrual regulation program. In Vietnam, Ipas was part of the Reproductive Health Project starting in 1994 with Pathfinder International and AVSC (now EngenderHealth), and Ipas Vietnam opened its own office in 2000. Vietnam programs focused on assisting the Ministry of Health in developing National Abortion Standards and Guidelines, and expanding access to comprehensive abortion care services, including safe, high quality second trimester abortion services. In India, Ipas played a strategic role in putting safe abortion on the national reproductive health agenda with a seminal conference on safe abortion in Agra in October 2000. With a major private grant, Ipas opened an office in New Delhi in 2001. After the law change in Nepal in 2002 to legalize abortion services, Ipas provided technical assistance in the development of policy guidelines, and planning and implementing the safe abortion program. Ipas's programs in Vietnam, India and Nepal expanded dramatically from 2000 - 2006. Ipas provided technical and training support to start comprehensive abortion care services in Cambodia in 2004 and began developing programmatic plans in Pakistan in 2006.
  Ipas's main strategy in Asia was to work in countries where abortion was legal to remove barriers to access and demonstrate models of quality comprehensive abortion care, including medication abortion primarily in India and Vietnam. Asian countries presented great potential for impact to improve women's lives through public sector programs and integration with other reproductive health initiatives.
  Don Weeden was Ipas's Regional Desk (Director) for Asia Programs starting in 1999, followed by Traci Baird in 2002, and Wendy Darby in 2005.
  - India 1988-2001: background files, PSS 88-94, corresp 95-99, trip reports 98 & 99, TAC abortion proposal 99, PRIME India 99-01, donor proposals/reports/corres 00, trip reports 00, country team mtgs 00, P Bhiwandi speech MVA congress 00, pop policy 00, PRIME II ANE 00, Famycare 00, MVA in India background paper 00, Janani/Liam 00-02, donor reports/reports/corres 01, program highlights/country report 01, trip reports 01, Ipas India presentation 01, Agra early abortion meeting working files 01, FOGSI/Ipas presentation 01, research papers 01, DV vs SV instruments 01, instrument specs 01, abortion in India lit review 01, Prastut consulting lit review and marketing report 01, marketing associate 01, marketing 01, MOH MVA guidelines 01, MIS program numbers 01, Contech 01, Dai Ichi Karkaria 01, marketing trip 01, Parkash 01, Mercator 01, Sisco 01, team mtgs 01, communication 01, DFID/SIDA proposal/comms/report 01, strategic planning 01, office materials 01, position descriptions 01, office setup 01-02, JMS 01-02, TA for AAP proposal 01-03, Romsons 01-04 (Box 96)
  - India 2002-2006: donor proposals/reports/corres 02, planning 02, env scan 02, program presentations 02, marketing research and plan 02, Romsons MOU 02, Krishnan consultancy 02, FOGSI workshops 02, Shah consultancy 02, TOT/scale-up/counseling materials 02, monitoring 02, GOI 02, office lease 02, team mtgs 02, Orissa workshops 02, country report 02, FOGSI presentation 02, trip reports 02, Bihar/Jharkhand (BJ) project 02-04, Eurodonor proposal 02-05, donor proposals/reports/corres 03, safe abortion workshop Delhi 03, program overview 03, program report 03, office lease 03, Eurodonor and staffing needs 03, WHO mtg 03, program review 03, TOT materials 03, TOT reports 03, results numbers 03, Pop Council 03-04, MTP Act changes 03-04, DFID logframe 03, program planning 03, team orientation 03, SIDA proposal 03, policy analysis 03, WHO guidance launch contract 03, Maharashtra donor proposal/report 03-05, donor proposal/reports 04, FOGSI 04, planning 04,Reserve Bank of India 04, MTP and NPP comparative analysis 04, small grants 04, Society registration 04, marketing 04, AAP 04, consultants 04-06, Ipas India pubs 04-06, Ipas in India report 05, MVA distribution 05, KVGK subcontract 05, Safe Abortion Care donor proposals/report 05-06, Maharashtra proposal 05-07, project updates 05-06, sex selection abortion presentation 06, marketing 06, Maharashtra planning 06, CAC donor proposal 06-09, Bihar/Jharkhand donor proposal 06-08 (Box 97)
  - Nepal 1995 - 2006: FHI legal reform project 95-96, PAC services report 96, AGI Nepal article review 01, Options 01, background articles/reports 01-02, MOH terms of reference 02, Policy/lit review 02, Human rights/maternal mortality report 02, lessons learned presentation 02, trip reports 02, Making AB safe and legal mtg 02, policy work 02, law amendment 02, CREPHA/Ipas concept paper 02, chrono 02-03, safe motherhood 03, Options TOR 03, Options proposal 03, Options 03, Options report 03, FWLD 03, TCIC contract 03-04, planning and comms 03-04, articles/reports 03-04, Potter contract 03-04, CREHPA contracts 03-06, chrono 04, Options 04, Maternity hospital 04, MA assessment 04, CAC training manual 04, RHTRA contract 04-05, TCIC/RHTRA contracts 04-05, general 04-05, Thomas contracts 04-05, DFID/SSMP reports 04-05, CAC monitoring 04-06, chrono 05, historical summary 05, chrono 05, donor proposal tech advisor 05, CREHPA proposal 05, briefing 05, CAC reference manual 05, options proposal 05, FWLD small grants 05, trip reports 05-06, Options agreement 05-06, articles/reports 05-06, Bird 05-06, TCIC reports 05-06, TCIC plan 05-08, corresp 06, CAC monitoring map data 06, CAC training MOH 06, CAC provider mtgs 06, Ipas in Nepal presentation 06, Maternal mortality study 06 (Box 98)
  - Vietnam 1988-1996: background 88-96, background 89-95, AVSC 89-99, corresp 90-97, FHI project 93, FHI AB study 93-95, FHI meetings 93-95, MOH comms 93-95, RHP development/proposals/reports 93-96, RHP trip reports 93-96, AVSC 93-96, Phamatech 93-96, trip reports non-Ipas 93-96, interagency mtg 94, Ipas background document 94, eval 94-96, Pathfinder comms 94-96, curriculum 94-95, RHP field reports 94-96, phamatech 94-96, Bourne corresp 94-96, RHP modules, RHPO MOU with MOH 95, Tyson 95-96, Ipas research 95-96, key memos 95-96, RHP misc reports 95-96 (Box 99)
  - Vietnam 1996-2000: site change plans 96, WHO assessment 96, RHP qtrly reports 96, Ipas country report 96, APHA panel 96, RHP mtg 96, RHP reports 96-97, M&E 96-97, comms 96-99, PACCOM 96-00, med records background 97, PHamatech 97, RHP working files 97, Hanh ICR 97, national standards workshop 97, RHIARC 97-98, trip reports non-Ipas 97-00, reach numbers 97-01, double valve study 98, donor reports 98, trip reports 98, country strategy 98, Hanh 98, field reports 98-99, 2nd trimester project 98-02, trip reports 99, educ mats 99, RHP report 99, donor reports 99, RHP qtrly reports 99-00, comms 99-00, team mtgs 99-00, RHP workplan 99-03, Ipas program overview 00, donor report 00, RHP MOU 00, RHP modules 00, RHP lessons learned 00, internal reports 00, World Bank 00, RHP strategic appraisal team 00-01, reports 00-01, trip reports 00, Quality of Care workshop report 00, RHP assessment reports 00-01, RHP reports 00-02, Ipas VN country team 00-01, RHP misc 00-03 (Box 100)
  - Vietnam 2001-2002: donor proposal 01, team retreat 01, donor report 01, RHP donor report 01, RHP appraisal 01, midwives workshop 01, service provider research study and presentation 01, needs assessment 01, reports 01, trip reports 01, RHP report 01, Dr. Loan presentation 01, WHO MA protocols 01, national RH strategy 01, demog info 01, marketing 01, results framework 01, CAC monitoring 91, reports 01, team mtgs 01-02, RHP general 01-02, donors comms 01-03, CAC WHO proposal 01-03, CAC monitoring 01-03, RHP mtgs 01-04, Comms 01-03, Admin misc 01-04, master plan 01-10, RHP planning and proposal 02, donor trip report 02, donor reports 02, trip reports 02, midlevel providers conf in SA 02, presentations 02, strategies 02, reports 02, WHO report 02, standards and guidelines 02, MOH 02, RHP training eval 02, instrument processing 02, CAC baseline 02, CAC donor reports 02, CAC monitoring 02, CAC manual 02, CAC partners mtgd 02-03, CAC donor report 02-03, PACCOM report 02-03, WHO CAC reports 02-03, RHP TA and workplan 02-03, Gender/adol/RH workshop 02-03, Pathfinder med educ proj 02-04, strategies 02-05 (Box 101)
  - Vietnam 2003-2006: CAC planning/corresp 03, CAC training 03, Adol Working Group 03, MVA video 03, stats 03, meetings 03, Gender TOT 03, donor report 03, RHP donor report 03, RHP report to Dutch 03, T&L reports 03, RHP youth proposal 03, longrange planning 03, program reviews 03, MOH bid 03, lease contract 03, license 03, numbers tracked 03, de Bruyn consultancy to RHP 03, Gender/adol/RH TOT 03, adol report 03, MA study/report 03, trip reports 03-05, RHP planning 03-04, EZ grip trial 03-04, PACCOM 03-04, CAC donor report 03, CAC donor proposal/corres 03-06, donor report 04, CAC planning/corres 04, Safe motherhood 04, planning forms 04, CAC report 04, dissemination 04, RHP proposal to dutch 04-06, CAC planning 04-06, CAC proposal 04-07, CAC project doc 04-07, med school safe AB project 05, workplans 05, Smart Women Clubs 05, partners mtg 05, intern 05, meetings 05, TSDI 05, Labeuf fellowship 05, CAC donor report 05, RHP donor report 05, CAC evals 05-06, data 05-06, CAC 06, RHP history and workplan 06, planning 06, activities 06, donor report 06, performance improvements 06, RHP presentation 06, Edelman consultancy 06, misc 06, donor report 06, scale up and e-learning 06 (Box 102)
  - Asia Miscellaneous Countries 1973-2006 (alphabetical): Afghanistan refugee proposal 02; Bangladesh MR training 87-98, MR Coordinating Comm 90-93, BAPSA 90-95, Women's Health Coalition 90-95, Mohammadpur Fertility Services 90-95, SIDA 91-97, Assoc. for Comm and Pop Research 93, Infection prevention report 93, FP and MCH logistics reports 94, program review 95, program report 96, PRIME proposal 98, misc 99, SIDS MR report 04, SRH report 05; Cambodia HS pilot project 01, trip report 04, UNFPA RH sub program 05, Health sector support program 05, USAID PAC 05, User fees background study, NRHP KAP study 05, AB estimates 05, data 05-06, background 05-06, planning 05-06, research brief 06, midwifery forum report 06, needs assessment 06; China background 98-00, Ipas White Paper 99, overview for board 01; Indonesia 06, Japan JOICFP 75, background 97-98, trip reports 97-98, donor strategies 98; Korea 73-78; Malaysia 00; Mongolia 00; Pakistan 01; Papua New Guinea 94; Philippines 02; Thailand 05-06; Turkey program development and planning 86-87, trip reports 86-92, Misc 88-90, contracts 90-92, Financioglu 90-92, Eval 90-91, field reports 90-92, proposal/reports 91-92, comms 91-94 (Box 103)
  - Asia Regional Management 2001-2006: strategic planning 01, presentations 01, strat planning results 02, sales analysis 01, teams roles 02, Safe Motherhood 02, development lessons learned 02, team mtgs 02, WHO/SEARO RH mtg 03, restructuring 03, CTL meeting 03, marketing 04, MVA launch plans 04-05, general corresp 04-06, regional planning 05, MAP 05-06, Board presentation 06, strategy and decision tree 06, expand impact 06, APCRSH planning 06, planning 06, trainers workshop 06, MVA 06, partnerships 06, team mtgs 06, trip reports 06 (Box 104)
- Training and Service Delivery Improvement (TSDI), 1988-2006, (5 boxes)
  - Informed consent 88-94; TOT sessions 89; complications 91; APHA paper 92; international collaboration 92-93; framework for combatting unsafe abortion 95; AVSC quality workshop 95; management/senior staff 95-01; Egypt 96; PAC materials 94-04; AVSC consultancy 97; PRIME in-services 97; PRIME 98; FEBRASGO 97-98; African RH priorities conference 98; PRIME SOPs 98; division mission/vision98; misc corresp and planning 98-02; Frontiers 98-99; Brazil 98-01; Africa Desk 99-00; RHTP technologies mtg 99; TSDI country responsibilities 99; PRIME partners mtg 99; LAC Desk 99-01; PRIME performance improvement 00; TSDI management 00; infection prevention 00; PAC Scaling Up meeting working files 00; country summaries 00; APHA abortion task force 00; Zimbabwe PAC 00; Elective abortion mtg 00 (Box 114)
  - TSDI unit files: FY 01-02 Matrix management input 01; PAC PRIME mtgs 01; results framework 01; Scaling up toolbox 01; divisional management 01; Francophone consultant 01; TSDI surveys 01; redefining TSDI 01; objectives/budgets/planning 01; planning/workplans 01; US 01-02; SMT work 01-02; Bosnia MVA training 01-02; Adolescents 01-02; infection prevention 01-02; 2nd trimester abortion 01-02; patient-provider interaction background 01-02; Kenya plans/projections/report 01-03; Training Task Force 01-05; adolescent working group 02; training vision statement 02; abortion/early pregnancy failure 02; contraceptive counseling 02; RH for refugees 02; training tools and guide 02; HIV/pregnancy/abortion 02; new MVA rollout 02; Francophone publications 02; PAC curriculum workshop 02; ESPS baseline 02 (Box 115)
  - TSDI: 02 ESPS 02; planning 02; PP training resources 02; capacity building workshop 02; training best practices conference 02; 63iii/scale up/Eurodonors 02; EuroNGO Paris mtg 02; Peru PAC 02; medical abortion 02-06; scaling up presentations 02; training toolbox 02-03; Africa Alliance 02-03; Scaling up 02-03; training M&E 02-03; Francophone work 02-03; Francophone instruments 02-03; TSID unit management 02-03; TSDI staff mtgs 02-04; Community and abortion/PAC 02-04; abortion counseling background 02-05; pain management background 02-05; HBME - UNC 02-05; MVA Plus launch training 02-05; HIV working group 02-04; sexual/gender-based violence 02-04 (Box 116)
  - TSDI: 03 Kenya PAC baseline assessment 03; TSDI objectives 03; medical abortion 03; training numbers 03; monitoring 03; values clarification workshop South Africa 03; TSID retreats 03; South Africa 03; ICPD + 10 03; Addis meeting 03; decision-making table 03; Quality of care/service delivery improvement 03; midlevel providers 03; presentations 03; Francophone budget 03; SAGO Bamako 03; effective training events curriculum 03; PAC CMW training Kenya; 03; APHA 03; Kenya capacity building workshop & TOT 03; CD Rom of MVA plus 03; Global Trainer Network 03-04; Mozambique research study 03-05; Ethiopia team 03-05; "equip" of Equip & Train 03-05 (Box 117)
  - TSDI: 04-06 Vietnam 2nd trimester 04; essential elements of PAC model 04; TSDI global mtg 04; TSDI corres 04; Exec Team 04; Peru midwives 04; misoprostol for PAC mtg 04; scale up summary 04; legal and ethical case studies 04; sustainability manual expert review 04; GTN 04; planning and review 04; march for Women's Lives 04; EC 04-05; WHO strategic approach 04-05; Partnership for Safe Motherhood and Newborn Health 04-06; South Africa team 04-06; Global Health Council 05; TA & In-service mentoring program 05; GTN eval 05; performance improvement 05; MAP results 05; MVA Plus launch 05; QA 05; MVA regulatory 05; e-learning 05; MA Task Force 05; WHO small grants 05; Mozambique 05; training strategies learnings 05; PAC resources 05-06; US program 05-06; Tunisia 05-06; Evals of trainers' workshops 05-06; performance and quality improvement 05-06; APHA presentations 06; annual directors mtg 06; Compac 06; MVA processing 06; TSDI/PPD 06; Journal Club 06; GEM reports 06; WHO technical consultation 06; TA and Mentoring program 06; Counting Abortion so that Abortion Counts mtg and reference manual 06 (Box 118)
- Policy Unit, 1991-2006, (4 boxes)
  Progressive abortion policies are critical for women to be able to exercise their sexual and reproductive rights and have access to comprehensive, woman-centered abortion care. In 1995, Ipas acquired the first dedicated funding to broaden efforts in the area of support for policy reform which allowed the formation of a technical unit with dedicated staff.
  Areas of focus and impact for Ipas's policy work include: integrating abortion into the agendas of other organizations working in the areas of health, human rights, and empowerment of women, including advocacy with professional associations such as the International Confederation of Midwives (ICM) and the International Federation of Gynaecology and Obstetrics (FIGO); advocating for the full implementation and liberal interpretation of current abortion laws; supporting local groups advocating for reforming restrictive abortion laws; supporting and creating social movements at all levels (global, regional, national) for sexual and reproductive health and rights, with a focus on safe abortion; building youth leadership and capacity in support of sexual and reproductive health and rights, including safe abortion; and monitoring and countering anti-choice activism.
  Of note is Ipas's work with multilateral agencies such as the World Health Organization and the United Nations. In 1998 Ipas gained Special Consultative status with the Economic and Social Council (ECOSOC) of the United Nations which allowed for participation in international conferences and other UN forums. Ipas staff have worked since then with the broader NGO community to advocate for progressive language in UN agreements on sexual and reproductive health and rights, including safe abortion. The Ipas policy unit has also focused thematic work on neglected issues including the intersection of unwanted pregnancy and abortion with women living with HIV/AIDS, adolescents, violence against women, and human rights. Ipas's policy work on administrative barriers in laws and policies helped shape the policy recommendations in the groundbreaking WHO guidance on safe abortion issued first in 2003. Ipas's policy work was created and developed under the direction of Charlotte Hord Smith.
  - Policy: 91-06/Policy unit strategic planning/development: new issues mtg 98-99; strat planning 91; program planning 98-06; gender 00; Ipas strat planning 00-02; country team leaders mtg 03; strat planning 05; mngmnt training; results framework 00; org development 99-06; external unit eval 06; SMT 00-02 Donor documents: donor comms 96-06; unit corresp 97-01; donor reports/proposals 96-03 Special topics & neglected issues: MWIA 95; women's groups 95-99; USAID & fp 96; CAs/coalitions corres 97-03; community level 98-02; intl NAF 99; South to South partnership 96-99; refugees 98; Men & SRH 94-97; induced/elective abortion 96-00; human rights and RH group 96-02; adolescents 98-02; opposition research 97-04; Global gag rule 01; HIV/AIDS 00-03; HIV/AIDS monitoring tool 04-05; violence 00-04; sex selection 06; conferences and mtgs 91-02; midlevel providers 03 Presentations and mtgs: presentations 96-03; Africa regional trainers mtg 94; AWID 96 & 02; CIDEM mtg 98; WHO safe abortion conference 01; presentation for Med students for Choice 03 (Box 120)
  - Policy: 94-06 Country-Specific Policy Work: Africa 96-04; Africa Alliance 02-06; Africa newsclips 05; Bolivia 98; Europe 03; Kenya 00-04; Women's Health Project Kenya 00; Guyana reform 96; Malawi Penal review 00; Namibia reform 96-98; Poland 97-98; South Africa 96-05; Nepal reform 94-04; Thailand 04; Research and publications: PRB Honoring commitments focus group 97; Romania research and pub 94; Abortion/adolescents/AIDS pub92-96; sustainability 96; research/publications 96-03; Resources/tools for policy/advocacy: legal updates and issues 96-06; legal updates and issues/corresp 96-01; advocacy resources 98-06; ethics resources 00-02; policy and advocacy analysis and eval 04-06 UN ECOSOC special consultative status: UN NGO background 95-01; ECOSOC 95-06; ECOSOC Qtrly reports 02 (Box 121)
  - Policy: 97-00 UN: UN trip reports 97-98; UN contributions 00-06 Commission on Status of Women: CSW 98; CSW 99; CSW outcome document 00; survey of LAC women's orgs 98 Beijing and follow-up conferences: Beijing + 5 expert group mtg 98; Beijing + 5 98-00; Beijing + 5 prep mtgs 99-00 ICPD and follow-up conferences: ICPD + 5 98; ICPD + 5 99-00; ICPD +5 Hague forum; ICPD + 5 background docs 99 WHO/UNFPA/UNICEF/World Bank/UNGASS on Children: UNGASS on Children 01; UNICEF 97; UNFPA 95-99; WHO 96-04; WHO technical consultation on safe abortion 96-98; World Bank 97-00 (Box 122)
  - Policy:96-06 Gender Task Force: GTF 99-02, GTF newsletters 00-01; GTF workshop evals 01; GTF follow-up 01 Midlevel providers/midwives/ICM: midwives 96-99; ICM communications 96-03; ICM core competencies 99-00; SA midwives conf 01; ICM Vienna 02; ICM PAC statements 02-05; IHCAR proposal 01-03; core materials; ICM core competencies comms 99-02; ICM Brisbane 02-05 Gender or Sex curriculum/youth training in SRH issues: GOS 01; GOS TOT 03; GOS curriculum; gender and media exercise; gender/adolescents/RH training Training/service delivery/policy issues: TSDI/Health systems 92-06; medication abortion task force 02-06; MVA sustainability 02-04; youth-friendly services 04; IEC materials 06 (Box 123)